[SPEAKER_00]: I'll start with this Majjhima Nikāya 151, Pindapāta Pārisuddhi Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: The purification of alms food is more like the collection of alms food purification practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on occasion, the Blessed One was living at Rajagaha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when it was evening, the Venerable Sariputta rose from meditation, went to the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_00]: After paying homage to Him, he sat down to one side, and the Blessed One then said to him, Sariputta, your faculties are clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: The color of your skin is pure and bright.
[SPEAKER_00]: What abiding do you often abide in now, Sariputta?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he replies, now, Venerable Sir, I often abide in suññata-vihāra, you know, emptiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is good, good, Sariputta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, indeed, you often abide in the abiding of a great man.
[SPEAKER_00]: For this is an abiding of a great man.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Sariputta, if a bhikkhu should wish, may I now often abide in emptiness, he should consider thus, on the path by which I went to the village for alms,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, in the place where I wandered for alms, or on the path by which I returned from the alms round, was there any desire, lust, hate, delusion, or aversion in my mind regarding forms cognizable by the eye?
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding any of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: If so, by... if by so reviewing he knows thus, on the path which I went to the village for alms,
[SPEAKER_00]: If there was desire, lust, hate and delusion in my mind, then he should make an effort to abandon those evil unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if by reviewing he knows thus, there was no desire, lust, hate or delusion, aversion in my mind regarding forms cognizable by the eye, then he can abide happy and glad, training night and day in wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I guess, there are many passages in the suttas like that, and see, like, most people sort of... well, they would either assume they already know it, or they would just read over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that's all a person needs to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's nothing, it's not a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep repeating, but it's not a magical, great, mystical secret that needs to be figured out through some novelty experience that you have, and, you know, rising of energy in your body and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that is relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the discernment of greed, aversion, delusion, and then not having it, not delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it rises on its own, you're mindful of it, until, having a reason, it has to cease, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... that's what it means he trains day and night.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't go day and night and repeats to himself, touching, touching, stepping, stepping, moving, moving, sitting, sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He keeps reviewing the experience as a whole, without the hour, attending to this, attending to that, moving this, step one, step two, step three.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keeps an eye, keeps the peripheral vision, as far as he can see, the background of his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there greed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there an inclination towards greed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there an inclination towards aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there an inclination towards delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: And by delusion, I mean distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many people don't even understand what delusion is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delusion is when it's obviously not sensual and not ill-will, but it's something that results in loss of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by definition, it's basically like indolence, mental indolence, or choosing a thing that will distract you from it, even if it's not unwholesome per se.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I would like to, you know, go and talk to wise people and maybe meet with some other monks and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's rooted in just desire to distract yourself from yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's the hardest to undo.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's it's not obviously unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to remove even even the slightest sort of layers of bad faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will kind of make you believe that you're really doing it for good reasons, while really you're just doing it to distract yourself from your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what it means he practices day and night.
[SPEAKER_01]: Day and night, he keeps a watchful eye on the horizon of his mind, basically, what's coming, if it's wholesome, if it's unwholesome, if it's not unwholesome, he delights, he abides gladly and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: He enjoys and he's quite happy and bright in that sense, because he knows exactly what he needs to do and he's doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As opposed to getting all caught up and wound up and intense, not knowing what he's doing, and then he's doing everything and nothing at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, you just get tied into a knot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you have a huge energy release, and then you think, wow, that was so powerful, and... And still, you're not a step closer to discerning the nature of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it present?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I fueling it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I maintaining it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I entertaining it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say that's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: He abides happy and glad, training night and day in wholesome states, which is the absence...
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of greed and aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's all he's seen, discerning the absence of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's discerning the absence of unwholesome states, and that is his abiding, and that is his meditation, that is his samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: That results in nibbāna, if developed fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't discern wholesome and unwholesome, and then he goes and does some meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, you know, helps him feel good or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But day and night, not like half an hour a day, from the morning he wakes up till he goes to sleep, he does not entertain and he's not negligent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just in regard to things that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things like greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things like... wanting, in a sense of sort of delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things like aversion, in a sense of rejecting it, trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And delusion, things like trying to distract himself from himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, aversion is not
[SPEAKER_01]: Aversion is basically trying to get rid of the spontaneously arisen sensual thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thought of a beautiful object, of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, it has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same, like sights come in the range of the eye, thoughts come in the range of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not your doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that it's not your doing, you will be trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be overstepping the mark.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like that simile of the bait, the deer herd, sutta, where... where the first... first herd sees how... sorry, the second herd sees the first herd, how they eat carelessly, as in engage in sensuality, and because of that, they're subjected to mara's control, but then they shun the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't discern the extent of mara's bait, but they say no to all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's usually the first response.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I must not.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not have this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sights are attachments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts are attachments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possessions are attachments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is attachment, because you can't differentiate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you want to throw all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that basically becomes your aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever these things arise, you always step your mark and you're shunning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you get hooked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because either way, you interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are much subtler layers of aversion than just hatred and irritation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have aversion in regard to your own senses and the objects that appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there is the pressure of a beautiful object.
[SPEAKER_01]: The prospect of it, and you reverse, because you, you know, you're afraid of the consequences and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, being afraid of the consequences is one thing, but then actually giving in to the aversion, and then actively trying to deny the thought, get rid of it, get rid of it, get rid of it, is, eh... it's rooted in aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's also unwholesome, and because of that, you keep engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sometimes there's a complete, you know, lack of mindfulness and the last bastion of your hope is just not breaking a virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yeah, you just have to endure it and say no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's like, you know, maybe once every in a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most, more often than not, people actually just cultivate aversion unknowingly through thinking they must be getting rid of this thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not the one responsible for debate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sutta doesn't say, oh, the deer sets up the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mara sets up the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sets up the beautiful object and enticing object that... that... that make the... make the deer herd trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start discerning the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha says, the final deer herd learns how to eat carefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they eat around the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you shun the bait, you get caught.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you eat carelessly, you get caught.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you learn how to eat carefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you're mindful in regard to that which can entrap you and you don't engage with it either through delighting in it or overly rejecting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You discern to allow... you learn how to allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a reason, you know it will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to actually do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how Mahārāja cannot see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because Mahārāja can see you only when there is a form of engagement in regard to the bait that he sets up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on the engagement, he can gauge where you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, look, he avoided it here, but he didn't avoid it there, or he completely ate carelessly, or he's trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's still interfering with my bait, so I know he's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then the final deer herd came, and there's absolutely food still there, no interference, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: So they... they're not interfering in the sense that they're trying to destroy the bait, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not interfering in the sense that they're trying to eat it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they must be somewhere, but Mahārāja can't see them now, because there is no response in regard to inciting objects, any senses or thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you go beyond centrality as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, back to the emptiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just real quick.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a place of like a bubble.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a mystical reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dimension of emptiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's absence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that other sutta I was reading the other day, the recording.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, he knows these things are absent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, he knows what's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's absence of certain things, that's what you're empty of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always a negative reference, emptiness, definition of emptiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, with the alms, you know, collection, alms going...
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't do...
[SPEAKER_00]: If he lives in the forest, or lives secluded, he goes amongst the people, and then sees... his mind gets lustful, his mind gets angry,
[SPEAKER_00]: He gets distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he comes back, he reviews.
[SPEAKER_01]: He reviews it, yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Comes back to seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't stand in the middle of the village.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't stay there, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and then start reviewing his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I cannot be stressed sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessity of physical seclusion, as in, the actual physical seclusion, when you know there is not even a... well, when you know when there isn't an easy prospect of people encroaching upon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, most likely, you'll be physically removed for the rest of the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like physical seclusion, go to a room and you close your door and you're surrounded.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this whole... having to go into the village for food, you know, there's... there's your...
[SPEAKER_00]: Opportunity to be around people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will give you more than enough to review for the rest of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you reviewed that there was nothing, nothing pulled you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're going to enjoy your seclusion even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.